Good morning. Today is March 26, it's the 28th of
אדר. Adar. Max Margulis filling in for Rabbi Linzer, and he should
be back tomorrow.
Today's דף daf is ס"ג Samech Gimmel in בבא בתרא Bava Batra
in the fourth פרק, perek, and we're going to pick up on
the fifth line from the two dots where it says פשיטא. pshita.
It's a little bit odd that the סוגיא sugya starts with the
word פשיטא. pshita. Usually, פשיטא pshita is an interjection part of the
way through to push the discussion forward.
In this case, I'm not really sure what the word פשיטא pshita
is adding to the סוגיא, sugya, but we'll see what the סוגיא
sugya says. פשיטא: pshita: אמר יחלוק פלוני בנכסי פלגא. amar yachlok ploni
benichsay palga. If someone says, as the רשב"ם Rashbam clarifies and other
ראשונים rishonim clarifies as well,
that this is a case of someone who is a שכיב מרע
shchiv mera who is dividing up property. Now, שכיב מרע, shchiv mera,
there's a bit of a debate. Is a שכיב מרע shchiv mera
just someone who is so sick that they have to be lying
down in bed, or is it someone who's specifically on their deathbed?
Obviously, the question with application to division of properties or to inheritances
and things like that would lead us to think it might only
be in a case where the person is, quote-unquote, on their deathbed
to the extent that they will be making these decisions for their
end of life plan.
But in some sense, we can never really know when a person
is so ill that they have to lie down, especially in גמרא
Gemara times, whether or not that will be the illness that takes
their life. And so the sense that these kinds of transactions are
taken at a time before they take effect, that is a person
makes some kind of a declaration, I want so-and-so to have this
property, I want to give this gift to so-and-so, and that will
only take effect at the time that they pass on. So in
fact, the application of the laws of שכיב מרע shchiv mera are
such that they're sort of conditional gifts or conditional sales. The other
important detail is that the שכיב מרע, shchiv mera, all of those
are מתנות matanot or transactions or קניינים kinyanim that are taken without
any formal process. It's something that takes effect entirely verbally, unlike almost
any other קניין, kinyan, and the question is whether that's something that's
empowered מדאורייתא mide'oraita or מדרבנן. miderabbanan. It's going to come up in
the ninth פרק perek and it'll be discussed there, but that's one
of the big questions. Is it really a דאורייתא de'oraita mechanism, something
connected to the idea of inheritance, or is it something that the
רבנן rabbanan made up in order to help solve people's end of
life estate issues in a way that would be more equitable or
at least more just to what they desire at that time? Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says: if you said יחלוק פלוני בנכסי, yachlok
ploni benichsay, someone should get, should split my properties, that's a half,
פלגא. palga. תנו
חלק לפלוני בנכסי, tnu chelek leploni benichsay, if you should say give
so-and-so a portion of my properties, so
מאי, mai, what is that? That's much more arbitrary. If you say
יחלוק, yachlok, he should split it, sounds like precise halves into two
halves. And we saw previously two days ago that נכסי nichsay means
even
houses, all sorts of real estate including houses and even slave property.
But if you just say give a portion to פלוני, ploni, we
don't know what portion you're talking about. Do you mean a twelfth?
Do you mean a one one-hundredth? Do you mean a half? It
could be all sorts of things. This is similar to the kinds
of cases we saw yesterday where some of the ambiguities of the
gift giving or of the sales lead to problems. Okay. So אמר
רבינא בר קיסי, amar Ravina bar Kissi, תא שמע. ta shema. So
רבינא בר קיסי Ravina bar Kissi quotes this ברייתא braita to support
his position. Now here's part of the problem. This is going to
be a ברייתא braita within the position of סומכוס, Sumchos, whose position
we know we do not adopt. סומכוס Sumchos is a student of
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, and his position in terms of cases of
ממון המוטל בספק, mamon hamutal besafek, cases of doubtful resolution of properties
or of monetary law, is יחלוקו, yachloku, it should always be divided
equally in a case of doubt. But רבנן, rabbanan, the general rabbinic
consensus opinion, disagrees with סומכוס Sumchos and says that the הלכה halacha
should follow
המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya, whoever is trying to
extract the property from whoever is in control of it has to
bring proof. That is, we retain a status quo position. So this
ברייתא braita is within the position of סומכוס Sumchos and that's why
all of the cases we're going to see are going to be
cases where the property is being split. However, the question we're interested
in is how much is How much is a חלק chelek considered
to be? So that's the question that רבינא בר קיסי Ravina bar
Kisi is asking on this line in the גמרא. Gemara. So he
says תא שמע דתניא. ta shma detanya. This is the ברייתא. braita.
האומר תנו חלק לפלוני בבור. Haomer tnu chelek l'ploni b'bor. Someone who
says, give so-and-so a portion, now again, this is the same ambiguous
לשון lashon we just saw: give a portion. So it's, we're unsure
what percentage it is, in a בור. bor. A בור bor is
a water cistern or a water pit in the ground. So סומכוס
אומר, Sumchos omer, what does he say? אין פחות מרביע. ein pachot
m'revia. לחבית. L'chavit. Sorry, if it's בבור, b'bor, if it is in
a בור, bor, that is, the way you described the amount of
water you were planning to sell him or the amount of water
rights was a חלק בבור, chelek b'bor, a portion of the בור.
bor. So סומכוס Sumchos says אין פחות מרביע. ein pachot m'revia. It's
not going to be less than a quarter. So let's figure out
why. So how do you decide how much more? Okay, so we
have to figure out. So minimally, right, a חלק, chelek, here's my
בור, bor, okay? So minimally, if I meant a חלק, chelek, it
could be the tiniest amount, just, you know, one percent, just the
tiniest piece. We were even saying potentially yesterday, like, you know, you
get the strip along. Correct, so in this case in the בור,
bor, the minimal amount is just the bottom, just the tiniest little
bit.
And
tiniest, not the top.
Whatever, not the bottom, I just mean like one percent, like one
or one very small portion. The rest of it will be בספק.
besafek. So סומכוס Sumchos says we split the rest. So that's why,
so that would be half of what's in dispute. So because he
said give a portion, we assume that the portion was itself half
of the entire thing. This is a half, this is a half,
so this is a quarter. And this is a little bit. So
it's a quarter plus. Okay, that's the argument. So this is what
is the חלק chelek
because the חלק chelek is a quarter plus a little bit. Sorry,
I don't get that. So the argument
again: so חלק chelek could mean the most minimal amount or it
could mean a half. So because it's סומכוס Sumchos and we have
a case of ספק, safek, it doesn't really mean the most minimal
amount. It just means a little amount or even a bigger little
amount. Right, so but that's the point, it could be anywhere from
a minimal amount up to a half. So the entire bit between
a little bit and a half is בספק, besafek, so you split
that, so he gets a quarter.
Think back to the first משנה mishna in בבא מציעא. Bava Metzia.
לתן חלק לששה וגם לשמנה. l'ten chelek l'shisha v'gam l'shmona. Could it
have been an eighth? So we're going to have the next case:
so because he said בבור, b'bor, in the בור, bor, that's what
he meant according to סומכוס. Sumchos. Now the next
case: לחבית, l'chavit, אין פחות משמינית. ein pachot m'shminit. So if it's
the amount that would be לחבית l'chavit to put into a barrel,
so that will be a smaller amount. The assumption is that the
לחבית l'chavit part would only be a quarter. So a quarter of
the whole thing, right? This is לחבית l'chavit and that's בספק. besafek.
Therefore you split it and you get only an eighth plus a
little bit. Okay, so that's the next part. So in other words,
this would be if the חלק chelek from the בור bor is
being designated to fill a חבית. chavit. Correct. I'm selling you מים
לחבית mayim l'chavit from my בור. bor. As opposed to simply saying
חלק בבור סתם. chelek b'bor stam. חלק בבור chelek b'bor could be
up to half the בור. bor. לחבית L'chavit will only be up
to a quarter of the בור. bor. And סומכוס's Sumchos general principle
is יחלוקו. yachloku. Right, so it's, where'd you get the little bit
from the bottom? Because most minimally, the חלק chelek would be the
little bit, that's not in dispute. Both sides agree that he sold
the most minimal amount.
So the quarter is, so he says אין פחות מרביע, ein pachot
m'revia, it can't be less than a quarter, or אין פחות משמינית,
ein pachot m'shminit, because he gets this little bit extra plus the
part that's in dispute. Okay, but what I'm not understanding is like,
you know, that eighth or whatever it is, it could be many
חביות. chaviot. So he says לחבית, l'chavit, how do you know he
doesn't mean... לחבית, L'chavit, the assumption is standard size of the חבית
chavit or standard water drawing practices is that לחבית l'chavit means a
quarter of the בור. bor. That's I guess, obviously,
that's the working assumption of this, of this discussion. We're going to
see the next case: לקדרה, likdeira, if he sells him water rights
to fill his pot, a cooking pot, so לקדרה אין פחות. likdeira
ein pachot. לקדירה, Likdera, if he sells him water rights to fill
his pot, a cooking pot, so לקדירה Likdera אין פחות מי"ב. ein
pachot mi-yod bet. It's not less than 1/12. So that again the
assumption is that the part that's being discussed is a sixth, so
therefore he'll get 1/12 plus no matter how big this בור bor
is. Correct, it's about presumably standard size. There was a friend of
mine who is in Israel and he didn't remember the modern Hebrew
word for a cooking pot and he used the word קדירה kdera
and someone was like no, no, no, no, no, you say סיר.
sir. So it was a little bit of a this is a
problem we have biblical Hebrew, we have Mishnaic Hebrew, we have modern
Hebrew. Okay.
So אין פחות מי"ב. ein pachot mi-yod bet. לתפיח, letafiach, if you
sell it for a drinking glass, רשב"ם Rashbam says כלי קטן לשתות
בו, kli katan lishtot bo, so לתפיח letafiach אין פחות משישה עשר.
ein pachot mi-shisha asar. He asked for a תפיח. tafiach. So then
you'll get only 1/16 because the part that's in debate is 1/8
of the בור. bor. So all of these different things, it makes
me think about Jenna is here, so I'm thinking about California.
So מיכל Michal I think of as Israeli, even though she's from
California also.
Okay, so חנן's Chanan also from California. Okay, so we have lots
of California. So I'm thinking about water rights in a drought time.
Not anymore, thank God, but so part of the question that comes
up is people think of their water needs mostly in terms of
drinking or maybe in terms of cooking, but in fact most of
your water use is for washing, laundry,
washing your dishes, and even more so in an industrial societal level,
the huge amount of water is used for manufacturing and agriculture and
all kinds of much bigger projects. So here the breakdown of different
kinds of things, לחביות lachaviot or בבור, babor, all these different things
going from large scale things that maybe are for animals or maybe
for agriculture and then going down to personal use, cooking, and then
drinking is actually a much smaller amount of the water. Okay. So
it sounds from this ברייתא braita again within the position of סומכוס,
Sumchus, but it seems to support that position that a חלק chelek
means different things based on sort of what the context was or
how it's being interpreted. So that was רבינא בר קיסי's Ravina bar
Kisi position. He said תא שמע ta shema that a חלק chelek
could mean a relatively small, it definitely means the most minimal amount
and it could mean up to many different sizes depending on the
context. So it could be very ambiguous. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. We
have a new ברייתא. braita. Wait, did he say תפיח tafiach was
a drinking glass? תפיח tafiach according to the רשב"ם Rashbam is a
drinking glass, yeah.
The רשב"ם Rashbam says כלי קטן לשתות בו בני אדם kli katan
lishtot bo bnei adam ושיעורא זוטא מכולהו, v'shiura zuta mikulhu, it's the
smallest of them all. Okay.
So תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. בן לוי, Ben Levi, this is a
complex case a little bit. There is a בן לוי Ben Levi
or a לוי, Levi, a guy, a Levite guy, שמכר שדה לישראל.
she-machar sade l'Yisrael. He sells his field to a ישראל. Yisrael. ואמר
לו על מנת שמעשר ראשון שלי. ve-amar lo al menat she-maaser rishon
sheli. He sells it on the condition that the rights to the
מעשר ראשון maaser rishon will be his. Now already I kind of
gave it away, but here's the problem.
On one extreme, if he didn't sell it at all, that is
if he totally retained rights to the land, then it can't count
as מעשר ראשון maaser rishon because מעשר ראשון maaser rishon has to
be part of the produce that then gets separated
by the owner and given to the לוי. Levi. So there now
we don't give it to the לוי Levi anymore because of עזרא,
Ezra, whatever, and ספק safek and all kinds of things. But basically
that's the mechanism. It has to belong to the ישראל. Yisrael. The
ישראל Yisrael has to separate the produce out and give it to
the לוי. Levi. So fundamentally the לוי Levi can't just be claiming
to retain property rights on 1/10 of the field. That's not what
he's trying to do. On the other extreme, if he is talking
about the מעשר ראשון, maaser rishon, he also can't be talking about
דבר שלא בא לעולם, davar shelo ba l'olam, that is something which
doesn't exist yet, the produce hasn't grown yet, the fruits aren't there
yet, it hasn't been separated, there is no מעשר ראשון maaser rishon
yet. So we have two polar extremes that are both problematic halachically.
I just want to clarify, I think I assumed
that לויים Levi'im didn't own land. Or wasn't there a previous problem?
So לויים Levi'im can end up owning land. So first, two things.
One is that the לויים Levi'im around their cities have a whole
מגרש migrash that they have, you know, they could have fields in
whatever. It didn't belong to any particular one. It doesn't, but they
could buy it, they could own it. But also a לוי Levi
could end up, he might not have an ancestral piece of land
that goes back to him in the יובל, Yovel, but he can
buy a piece of land. So a לוי Levi could end up
being a plantation owner with billions of דונם dunam of produce and
still get מעשר ראשון? maaser rishon? Yes, as long as he gives
it back at the end of the שמיטה, shmita, at the end
of the יובל Yovel year, right? Like everybody else. Like everybody else.
So I don't think I quite ever really realized that. Really so
dependent on society necessarily. Well, it depends. It's possible they were. It
all depends, right. The assumption in the תורה Torah is that the
לויים Levi'im would be relatively poor. destitute and would need the social
security net of the... just for the rich guys.
Right. Well, is every גר Ger poor? Is every אלמנה Almanah poor?
Not necessarily. So there are basic assumptions in the תורה, Torah, there
are people who maybe need additional protections legally, even if they're not
poor, because there are other ways they could be exploited, but it's
a complexity. Well, it's something they had as land-owning,
produce-owning לוי. Levi. Presumably. At least he owns this one field, okay?
Okay. Can they marry somebody else? Who, a לוי? Levi? Because this
is right now the בן לוי, ben Levi, so could his land
come from... It could come from his mother's father, that's also true,
he could have inherited from his grandfather. I don't know how to...
So when he has all this, let's say he's really wealthy and
he has children, does that wealth pass on to his children? For
sure, like anyone else. He can give inheritance. But it's again, if
it's a field it goes back in יובל, Yovel, doesn't make a
difference. Right. Anyway, the assumption is nowadays we live without a יובל
Yovel year, so it removes some of the complication. Yeah. The תורה
Torah says he's not going to get a possession in the land,
right? Possession means a חלק, chelek, means a permanent ancestral holding. Right.
And even when they were conquering the land, you know, this is
now, you know, the initial years. Anyway, it's many years later, right.
The case is, the point is that this is the problem. The
problem is we have two problems. If it's something very intangible that
he's retained, like the right to collect the produce once it is
later separated, that's דבר שלא בא לעולם, davar shelo ba l'olam, something
that doesn't exist yet. We have a principle you're not allowed to
sell something that doesn't exist yet. That's one extreme. Well, this is
per decio maybe? And things like that, so how much is it
assumed to already exist and things like that, and there are lots
of סוגיות sugyot about that. And the other extreme is if he's
really retaining full property rights of one-tenth of the land, well then
it's not מעשר ראשון ma'aser rishon because it has to have been
owned by the ישראל Yisrael and then separated. So the way the
ריטב"א Ritva explains and the רשב"א Rashba explains a little bit similarly,
that it is very much an abstract legal right of, I'm retaining
the rights that I will be the לוי Levi that you give
the מעשר ראשון ma'aser rishon to when you separate מעשר ראשון. ma'aser
rishon. That's what to me... Right. So but you have to clearly
articulate that legal right separate from the property ownership in the land
or in the produce because either of those has no problem, right?
Right, so that's what he's saying here. That's the only way to
understand the סוגיא, sugya, seemingly. So he's not selling it in דבר
שלא בא לעולם? davar shelo ba l'olam? He's, right, he's selling everything
except a דבר שלא בא לעולם, davar shelo ba l'olam, that means
he's retaining ownership of something which doesn't really have a tangible... but
I see what Jenna is saying, that he's not actually selling it,
right, he's keeping a דבר שלא בא לעולם, davar shelo ba l'olam,
that's actually an interesting חילוק, chiluk, I like that. Okay, so בן
לוי שמכר שדה
לישראל ואמר לו על מנת שמעשר ראשון שלי. ben Levi shemachar sadeh
l'Yisrael v'amar lo al menat shema'aser rishon sheli. מעשר ראשון שלו, ma'aser
rishon shelo, he gets to keep the מעשר ראשון. ma'aser rishon. That
is presumably at the time when it grows and the owner harvests
it and everything, and then he gives it back to him. There
is a problem, a similar problem, there's a discussion of כהן המסייע
בבית הגרנות. kohen hamisayeia b'veit hagranot. What if the כהן kohen goes
to the threshing floor to try to help out, hoping that he'll
be given the תרומה trumah by the field owner? And is there
complications around that or not, because part of the question is that
the owner really should retain the rights to give the תרומה trumah
to whichever כהן kohen he wants, and then if this כהן kohen
is trying to manipulate the system, it gets a little bit thorny.
So there are a lot of סוגיות sugyot about that as well.
Okay, ואם אמר לי ולבני, v'im amar li ulvanai, if he said
when selling it, I want to be retained the rights to the
מעשר ראשון ma'aser rishon for myself and for my descendants in the
future, my לוי Levi sons in the future. So מת יתן לבניו,
met yitein livanav, if he dies, it should be given to his
sons. ואם אמר לו כל זמן שהשדה זו בידך מכרה וחזר ולקחה
אין לו עליו כלום. v'im amar lo kol zman shehasadeh zo biyadecha
machra v'chazar v'lakcha ein lo alav klum. And if he said, as
long as this field is in your possession, then if the purchaser
sells it to someone else and buys it back, then that nullifies
the deal because it left his ownership. So even though it came
back to his ownership, it was under new conditions.
The middle case is interesting, the case of the בנים, banim, because
this legal right to the מעשר ראשון ma'aser rishon is actually something
that can be transferred by inheritance, which is something we might not
have thought. It might be that properties could be transferred by inheritance,
but not שעבודים shibudim like debts and intangible legal rights to
a certain property or something like that. So here this is a
very interesting סוגיא sugya for expanding into a much more, I think,
much more modern notion of ownership that goes into much less tangible
real estate, but much more about the rights to the produce and
the rights to futures and things like that. Okay, so אין
לו עליו כלום. ein lo alav klum. אמאי? amai? אין אדם מקנה
דבר שלא בא לעולם. ein adam makneh davar shelo ba l'olam. So
you can't transfer something that doesn't exist yet, so therefore,
because the person selling the land to a third party cannot then
transfer that legal requirement to give the מעשר ראשון ma'aser rishon to
this לוי. Levi. and then have him transfer it back to him
in the future. That's something that couldn't be sold. So I actually
like the last case, the last case. That's why actually I very
much like Jenna's point, I hadn't thought of that, which is that
the initial case is him retaining ownership of a דבר שלא בא
לעולם, davar shelo ba l'olam, but the problems arise when you try
to sell a דבר שלא בא לעולם. davar shelo ba l'olam. So
that's part of the difference. Okay, כיון דאמר ליה על מנת שמעשר
ראשון שלי. keivan d'amar lei al m'nat shema'aser rishon sheli. The whole
reason why it works is because you said על מנת, al m'nat,
on the condition that it be retained. Okay. So we therefore understand
from his language, his use of the words על מנת, al m'nat,
שיורי שייריה למקום מעשר. shiyurei shayreia limkom ma'aser. He retained the rights
to the place of the מעשר. ma'aser. Now that gets into what
I was saying before. How can it be that he retains the
rights in the land, the place, the מקום מעשר, makom ma'aser, the
place where the מעשר ma'aser fruits are growing, but then it won't
be מעשר ma'aser because he owns the land? So it's a little
bit more intangible, at least as how the ראשונים rishonim understand it,
it has to be he has rights to the produce that grows
on that land without it actually being his. Okay.
So based on the language of זכות, zechut, זכויות? zechuyot? It wasn't
used in the סוגיא sugya here as far as I could tell.
It's used in the ראשוני. rishoni. Is that the term, as a
rights to something? Not necessarily.
Here I don't think it was, it was much more just about
how his ownership of the מעשר ma'aser translates into ownership of the
properties.
But it's a little bit tricky. Meaning, I understand what we're saying
here, but so how, exactly how is the ראשוני rishoni getting around
it? Because it's trying to clarify, trying to clarify what middle ground
you have legally to stand on where the rights to the מעשר
ראשון ma'aser rishon are not totally intangible so that it's דבר שלא
בא לעולם, davar shelo ba l'olam, and the reason it's not intangible,
why? Because it is an articulated right to produce that will be
produced by this particular piece of field. But it's intangible because it's
not there. So right, so that's part of what they're struggling with.
I don't think the answer is so clearly articulated that it's airtight,
but it's certainly its development. It's the answer the רשב״ם Rashbam would
say, but it doesn't seem like that would
work הלכתית, halachically,
unless
you
just
say
like, okay,
there's
a problem but we don't care.
Right, well, we do care, right. Yes. רשב״ם Rashbam says זכות. zechut.
So he says זכות. zechut. Great. מעשר ראשון שלו ואפילו מכרו לוקח
לאחר דזכותו של לוי אינו יכול למכור לאחר דאכתי ברשותו קאמר. ma'aser
rishon shelo va'afilu macharo lokei'ach l'acher d'zechuto shel levi eino yachol limkor
l'acher d'achti birshuto ka'amar. Right. Okay. Conceptualized, it's about
the fact that the לוי levi retains the rights to the properties,
to the מעשר. ma'aser. Now again, part of this is complicated, of
course, by the fact that the לוי levi can't demand that you
give him the מעשר ma'aser because we say generally that the לויים
leviyim nowadays
are ספק, safek, we don't know that they're לויים, leviyim, and a
ישראל yisrael is allowed to eat מעשר. ma'aser. So there are other
reasons why the מעשר ma'aser nowadays generally we don't give to the
לויים, leviyim, but at least in the גמרא Gemara times I think
they did. Okay. Yeah. Were you saying in the example you gave
about the כהן kohen going to the threshing floor, yeah. So is
it also applicable here? In other words, is does the owner of
the land
have the right to decide who to give the מעשר ראשון ma'aser
rishon to? Presumably, under a normal case, the owner of the field
would be allowed to give to whichever לוי levi he wants. Part
of the issue is exactly that, that in this case he's been,
can this לוי levi demand it or not? And we're going to
see. It sounds like in this case, yes. And then we're getting
into other cases that maybe are more the rights or we actually
had previously also, right? Like on ס״א, samech alef, there were some
cases like that as well. Okay. Base, our conclusion is you can
just tell anyone anything you want, וכל תנאי, v'chol tnai, as long
as it's whatever. As long as you specify it clearly and as
long as it's written into the agreement and everything like that. At
least this kind of right, but it has to be well articulated
and part of the work that the ראשונים rishonim had to do
was to explain what what the parameters of this kind of a
legal right are separate from property ownership and separate from a futures,
which we would say most kinds of futures generally aren't acceptable in
הלכה. halacha. Okay. אמר ריש לקיש זאת אומרת המוכר בית לחברו ואמר
לו על מנת שדיוטא העליונה שלי דיוטא העליונה שלו. amar reish lakish
zot omeret hamocher bayit l'chavero v'amar lo al m'nat shediyuta ha'elyona sheli
diyuta ha'elyona shelo. This implies that if someone sells so presumably based
on the ברייתא braita we just saw about the לוי levi selling
the field and retaining the rights to it, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
says if someone sells a house and says it's על מנת al
m'nat that the upper story stays mine, then the upper story should
stay his. That is, we originally thought that when you sell a
house you sell the entire house, but if you make explicit that
you're retaining rights to the upper story, then then great, you can
retain rights to the upper story. It seems like why is that
such a חידוש, chiddush, right? The גמרא's Gemara going to have kind
of that question. So למאי הלכתא, l'mai hilchata, what is this coming
to tell us? That is, it's almost obvious. So רב זביד אמר
שאם רצה להוציא בה זיזין מוציא. rav zevid amar she'im ratza l'hotzi
bah zizin motzi. If you want to build little prongs, little ledges
off of the upper story or off of the roof area you
can, even though that's going to, you might have thought that you
only have it in the way it is and no alteration rights.
Right, and you even have rights to make alterations. So להוציא בה
זיזין מוציא. l'hotzi bah zizin motzi. רב פפא אמר שאם רצה לבנות
עליה על גבה בונה. Rav Pappa amar she'im ratzah livnot aliyah al
gabah boneh. And רב פפא Rav Pappa says if you want to
build a third story, you could build a third story even. That
is, the construction rights are very substantial. Okay, so בשלמא bishlama ד-רב
זביד, de-Rav Zvid, היינו דקתני hainu de-tani זאת אומרת. zos omeres. So
I understand רב זביד Rav Zvid because זאת אומרת zos omeres is
kind of like an additional like a little step like a corollary
case. However, אלא ella ל-רב פפא, le-Rav Pappa, מאי mai זאת אומרת?
zos omeres? For רב פפא Rav Pappa who says you could build
a third story on the building, is it really like a זאת
אומרת zos omeres kind of a case? It's not really comparable. The
גמרא Gemara says קשיא. kashya. Like, we know what רב פפא Rav
Pappa said, it doesn't really fit the language in the of what
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said, but רב פפא Rav Pappa thought it
did. So okay. Wait, I don't I don't get that. That's fine.
That is זאת אומרת zos omeres is usually like about a relatively
parallel kind of a corollary type of a case. So here we
were comparing the retaining the rights to build on the upper story
of the house to retaining the rights to the מעשר ראשון ma'aser
rishon in the field, but רב פפא, Rav Pappa, רב זביד's Rav
Zvid point is that it's sort of a minimal kind of a
case, you can build the out jutting ledges and things like that.
For רב פפא Rav Pappa to be able to build an entire
additional story on the building substantially changes the nature of the building
and the nature of the person who bought the ground floor, so
that's a little bit, it's not so comparable. So the גמרא Gemara
says קשיא, kashya, it's not, you know, you could work it out,
but we're not going to. Like I know I understand that this
is like a really common word here but what does דיוטא dyuta
mean? דיוטא dyuta is is the is like the upper terrace of
bricks I think, right? It's like the top top layer of bricks.
So it means the upper layer. Like I remember it from the
from the משנה Mishna in שבת Shabbat or the גמרא Gemara in
שבת Shabbat about the מלאכה melacha of בונה boneh I think also
used the same words to talk about the rows of bricks. So
דיוטא עליונה, dyuta elyonah, is there a word in English for that,
for a row of bricks? A course? A course of bricks, good,
right. Yeah, so basically he has the roof, basically he has the
roof with the building rights to continue construction off of the... right,
not the upper story, right, it's a one-story house. Right, it's a
right, the air rights to the top roof of the house. Right,
okay. Well if it's the roof, well I guess because you could
have said the bottom one. Because not just the גג, gag, right?
It's not just I have rights to use the גג gag for
putting my figs there to dry out. It's that I have the
rights for construction rights from the roof going up, which is a
much bigger kind of rights. Okay. תנו רבנן tanu rabanan is like
basically a ברייתא. braisa. תנו רבנן tanu rabanan is almost always a
ברייתא braisa I think. I would think it would be a ברייתא.
braisa. Why? So why, what, what does it say דתניא de-tanya versus...
there's a whole discussion of why it's תנו רבנן tanu rabanan and
why it's דתניא de-tanya and I think sometimes in manuscripts they interchange.
Is there really no reason? There's not so real reason, yeah. Some
people like to teach people at least that תנן tnan always means
a משנה Mishna and תניא tanya always means a ברייתא braisa and
even that's not always precise in the manuscript. They're just very synonyms.
That's the best way to say it. But generally it's... they must,
maybe someone who knows a lot more גמרא Gemara than me understands...
תנן tnan is usually the משנה, Mishna, but well, in our version
it's been amended to say תנן tnan when it's a משנה Mishna
and תניא tanya when it's a ברייתא. braisa. But it wasn't always
that way. תנו רבנן tanu rabanan was always saying more or less
it's a ברייתא, braisa, the same as דתניא. de-tanya. If the word
is of course, a course of bricks, good, right. Yeah, what's the
function of תנו רבנן? tanu rabanan? דתניא de-tanya is always going to
be I'm going to bring a proof from this thing. תנו רבנן
tanu rabanan usually introducing a new a new ברייתא, braisa, not in
continuation of the previous thought. Okay. אמר רב דימי מנהרדעא. Amar Rav
Dimi mi-Neharde'a. So רב דימי Rav Dimi from נהרדעא Neharde'a said: האי
מאן דמזבין ליה ביתא לחבריה, hai man de-mizban leh beisa le-havreh, someone
who sold sells a house to his friend, אף על גב דכתב
ליה af al gav de-chasav leh עומקא ורומא, umka ve-ruma, even though
in the שטר shtar you wrote that you're selling עומקא ורומא, umka
ve-ruma, the depths and the heights, that is the excavation rights and
the air rights, צריך למכתב ליה tzarich le-michatav leh קני לך מתהום
ארעא ועד רום רקיעא. kani lach me-tehom ar'a ve-ad rum reki'a. You
have to say explicitly, I'm selling you from the depths of the
earth until the heights of heaven. That is עומקא ורומא umka ve-ruma
סתם stam doesn't mean anything. But you have to explicate that it
means מתהום ארעא ועד רום רקיעא, me-tehom ar'a ve-ad rum reki'a, all
the way down and all the way up. So why are you
saying it? Ah, we're going to see. We're going to see. So
מאי טעמא mai ta'ama ד-עומקא ורומא de-umka ve-ruma בסתמא לא קני? bistama
lo kani. So why is what's the reason? Because עומקא ורומא umka
ve-ruma just by itself לא קני, lo kani? nothing is added, there's
no additional purchase or or declaration of of acquisition being made by
mentioning עומקא ורומא. umka ve-ruma. So הני hanei עומקא ורומא umka ve-ruma
למקנה, עומקא ורומא Lemeknaye umka veruma אהני ahanei מתהום ארעא ועד רום
רקיעא? me-tehom ar'a ve-ad rum reki'a? So in this case where we're
talking about in the house for example, so the עומקא ורומא umka
ve-ruma you would just think that just sort of means the the
depth of the floor of the house and the height of the
roof of the house. That is it's just sort of the normal
point. So you would have to say מתהום ארעא ועד רום רקיעא
me-tehom ar'a ve-ad rum reki'a למקנה, le-mikneh, to be able to sell
those, that is actual air rights and the actual excavation rights underneath,
you would have to say... No, why would you think meaning if
I was just selling my house, I'm saying I'm selling you my
house, of course it includes the floor and the ceiling. So if
so if I say עומקא ורומא, umka ve-ruma you're saying this is
the same thing? Because עומקא ורומא umka veruma, sounds like it means
you're clarifying that you mean all the way down to the bottom
of the house and all the way up to the top of
the house. Sell you my house, what else would you have thought?
To the upper roof, right, of the building, or of the עלייה,
alia, yeah, excavation. But we think it means nothing though. It means
nothing. He says בסתמא bi-stama לא קני. lo kani, If you just
say עומקא ורומא, umka veruma it means nothing. Right, so that's what
I'm saying. So like, but if I just wanted to give you
my house, I would have just said my house. I'm saying עומקא
ורומא umka veruma, my house, I'm still saying the same thing. You're
still saying the same thing. But then why am I going through
because in other cases it does mean something. Chana, what's your point?
You have to know how words are used in that context, in
that context, in that language. Right, so I mean this is like
this is the thing. Right. And these are phrases that are used
in normal contracts, so they're parsing the contract. The problem was yesterday
when you said extra things, we were thinking, oh it does mean
a little extra and we're trying to figure it out, now we're
saying it means nothing. So in this context it means nothing. Okay.
בור ודות ומחילות. bor vedut umichilot. I don't really know if it's
about different kinds of holes and water water tanks and things like
that. So in those cases, what do we say about עומקא ורומא
umka veruma in the case of a בור bor and a דות
dut and things like that? לימא מסייע ליה leima mesaye lei בלא
את הבור ולא את הדות. belo et habor velo et hadut. If
you that it doesn't include, that is going back to the משנה,
mishna, right, if we had from the original משנה, mishna, no? I
thought it was. Yes. Sorry, what's a דות? dut? A דות dut
is also a water tank, no? Is that just the same word
like in on ראש השנה Rosh Hashana with like you hit a
שופר shofar בהדות? bahadut? You know that word, you know, the echo?
It's like from inside... Oh, in a דות, dut, right, you blew
it into a דות dut like a, yeah, like a water barrel
or something, right. In ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, yeah. So you're saying
it's from our liturgy on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashana. Yeah, it was
like, what, it was from our liturgy. Yeah, it was one of
those ספרדי Sephardi פיוטים piyutim or something, you know. I thought it
was in the משנה, mishna, but now it's not, it's not in
the משנה. mishna. I got confused. מהני עומקא ורומא למקני בור ודות.
mahani umka veruma lemakni bor vedut. Right, right. Meaning if you said
that, then you get it. Right. It's the following, next משנה. mishna.
Yeah, yeah. Oh, it's the next משנה, mishna, that's why, that's why
I got confused. Okay. סייעא, saya, okay fine. ולא את הבור ולא
את הדות. velo et habor velo et hadut. So the next משנה,
mishna, if you look for tomorrow's דף, daf, the next משנה mishna
says when you sell the house, ולא את הבור ולא את הדות
אף על פי שכתב לו עומקא ורומא. velo et habor velo et
hadut af al pi shekatav lo umka veruma. So that's part that's
what we're getting into now. We're preempting tomorrow's משנה. mishna. So you
that is if you say עומקא ורומא umka veruma it doesn't sell
the בור bor and the דות. dut. That is presumably because they're
dug underneath the house or something like that. I don't know exactly.
Beneath the home, whatever it is. I don't know exactly what. No,
but you say you just said it. Right. Unless you say מתהום
ארעא mitehom ara that goes all the way down, right. So לימא
מסייע ליה, leima mesaye lei, maybe this should support that position, that
is a משנה mishna from the next דף. daf. ומחילות. umichilot. מחילות
michilot are tunnels, yeah. And what's the difference? Yeah. So ולא את
הבור ולא את הדות אף על פי שכתב לו עומקא ורומא velo
et habor velo et hadut af al pi shekatav lo umka veruma
ואי סלקא דעתך ve'i salka daitach בסתמא קני bistama kani עומקא ורומא
umka veruma ליהני עומקא ורומא למקני בור ודות ומחילות. leihani umka veruma
lemakni bor vedut umichilot. So then you should say that if you
said just עומקא ורומא umka veruma by itself, then it should allow
you to acquire the בור bor and the דות dut and the
מחילות, michilot, which the משנה mishna explicitly says not. So that's a
לימא מסייע ליה, leima mesaye lei, so לימא מסייע ליה leima mesaye
lei usually is going to be rejected. So let's see. דלא כתב
ליה. delo katav lei. Because the משנה mishna said that you didn't
write it. והא אף על פי שכתב לו קתני. veha af al
pi shekatav lo katani. And the משנה mishna says even if you
did write it. That is if you even if you did write
עומקא ורומא. umka veruma So it sounds like עומקא ורומא umka veruma.
means nothing. הכי קאמר. hachi ka'amar. This is how we should read
the משנה. mishna. אף על פי שלא כתב לו. af al pi
shelo katav lo. Even if you didn't write עומקא ורומא, umka veruma
כמי שכתב דמי. kimi shekatav dami. It's like you wrote it. Okay.
למקניא עומקא ורומא ולמקנא בור ודות ומחילות. lemikneya umka veruma ulemikne bor
vedut umichilot. That is even if you don't write מתהום ארעא ועד
רום רקיעא, mitehom ara ve'ad rum rakia, it is as if you
did when you write just עומקא ורומא, umka veruma, such that you
would acquire the בור bor and the דות. dut. We've totally reversed
the way to read the משנה. mishna. That is, it's a הכי
קאמר, hachi ka'amar, we've changed changed the משנה mishna to make it
make sense. But it's the same thing as what I was saying.
So in other words, the reason why you wrote it means it
must help. It must help a little bit. At least to get
you the בור bor and the דות dut and the מחילות, michilot,
which are part of the structure, but presumably not further down or
or much higher up or things that haven't been actualized yet, air
rights and things like that. Okay. אע"ג דלא כתב ליה ככתב דמי
עומקא ורומא ומקני בור ודות ומחילות. af al gav delo katav lei
kechatav dami umka veruma umakne bor vedut umichilot. אי כתב ליה. i
katav lei. Is this what we're saying we actually should interpret or
maybe... Yes, הכי קאמר. hachi ka'amar. והכי קאמר vehachi ka'amar is to
respond to the לימא מסייע ליה. leima mesaye lei. So the לימא
מסייע ליה leima mesaye lei could go either way. And they're saying
no, it might not. No right, we're rereading the no, we're rereading
the משנה mishna to contradict the previous way. So that is we
said אף על פי שלא כתב לו, af al pi shelo katav
lo, even if you don't explicate that עומקא ורומא umka veruma, means
אומקא דתהום ועד רומא דרקיעא, umka detehom ve'ad ruma derakia, it's כמי
שכתב. kimi shekatav. it's as if you wrote it. So this gets
into what we were talking about a little bit yesterday about the
legalese, that is, sometimes the way legalese works is there's certain conventions,
and when you write עומקא ורומא umka veruma even if it's an
ambiguous phrase or if it's something that's not explicit, we can assume
that it has a certain semantic context in the legal contracts of
the time to mean a certain thing. So אף על פי שמי
שכתב דמי. Af al pi shemi shekatav dami. Let's pass through this
mishnah. So what- how do we interpret the next mishnah? ולא את
הבור ולא את הדות Velo et habor velo et hadut and you
do not get the bor and the dut אף על פי שכתב
לו עומקא ורומא Af al pi shekatav lo umka veruma means now
we're saying אף על פי שלא כתב לו כמי שכתב דמי. Af
al pi shelo katav lo kemi shekatav dami. If you didn't write
it, it's like you did write it למקנה עומקא ורומא lemikne umka
veruma. למקנה בור ודות ומחילות. Lemeknaye bor vedut umachilot. So the גמרא
Gemara continues, אי כתב ליה עומקא ורומא, Ei katav leh umka veruma,
if you just write עומקא ורומא, Umka veruma קני, Kani, then you
have acquired it. אי לא כתב לא קני. Ei lo katav lo
kani. And if you didn't write it, then you don't acquire it.
So that seems to be not like that. So let's see. So
now we have תא שמע. Ta shema. תא שמע Ta shema is
going to help us clarify this question. So תא שמע Ta shema
says עומקא ורומא Umka veruma, as applied to a בור ודות ומחילות
Bor vedut umachilot which are some kind of underground constructions underneath the
house. So it's an exploration now of excavation rather than air rights.
Right, rather than air rights, right. But it's עומקא ורומא, Umka veruma
so רומא Ruma is talking about the air rights also. Okay, so
we say תא שמע ולא את הגג בזמן שיש לו מעקה גבוה
עשרה טפחים. Ta shema velo et hagag bizman sheyesh lo ma'akeh gavoha
asara tefachim. So the משנה, Mishnah, our משנה Mishnah had said if
you sell the house, you don't necessarily intend to sell the roof
rights if it has a מעקה Ma'akeh that is עשרה טפחים Asara
tefachim high. Meaning you're selling the house with a structure on it
that indicates its construction is finished. Right, I'm going to draw a
picture. No, I'm not selling you the rights to take down that
מעקה Ma'akeh and build up. Right. So this is my house and
I have a מעקה Ma'akeh on top. It has a very nice
מעקה. Ma'akeh. So when I sell the house, I get to keep
the מעקה Ma'akeh because this is a useful roof with the מעקה.
Ma'akeh. I can do stuff up here. Is that your fence? I
can put a nice ladder here, you know the whatever the צורי
Tzori not the מצרי Mitzri ladders. Oh, no, not מצרי. Mitzri. And
then, right? So it'll be good. I'll be able to use the
גג, Gag, the person who buys the house can keep the בית
Bayit and we'll all be good. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
תא שמע ולא את הגג בזמן שיש לו מעקה גבוה עשרה טפחים.
Ta shema velo et hagag bizman sheyesh lo ma'akeh gavoha asara tefachim.
I liked to draw that picture. I like drawing the picture. ואי
סלקא דעתך בסתם קני, Vei salka dach de'atach bistam kani, if you
think that when you state it בסתם, Bistam, that is just, I'm
selling you the house, קני עומקא ורומא, Kani umka veruma, if you
think that just not mentioning עומקא ורומא Umka veruma, at all would
still acquire you עומקא ורומא, Umka veruma כי גבוה עשרה טפחים מאי
הוי כיון דגבוה עשרה טפחים חשיב. Ki gavoha asara tefachim mai havei
keivan degavoha asara tefachim chashiv. So maybe you should say that no,
I would acquire the roof rights when you just sell, I'm selling
you my house, would that include the roof? So you would say
maybe yes, but we say no, because the מעקה Ma'akeh is עשרה
טפחים Asara tefachim high, that makes it a separate area that is
חשיב, Chashiv, that is considered separately, that's important enough to be considered
separately. Like a parking space in the building or something. Right, a
parking space is sort of a separate piece of property that's not
considered connected or sold along with the apartment. No, but would you
keep it if you're not in the building? So the point is
presumably if the מעקה Ma'akeh were too short, and now again that's
a halachic problem as well to have a מעקה Ma'akeh that's too
short. But it would also mean that the roof is not considered
as a separate usable area because the מעקה Ma'akeh is too short
halachically if it's less than עשרה טפחים, Asara tefachim, it's a dangerous
roof, you wouldn't use it. So then when you sell the house,
then it would be sold through. So that sounds like a proof
from our משנה Mishnah that סתמא, Stama, not saying עומקא ורומא, Umka
veruma, includes עומקא ורומא Umka veruma, anyway, because you would retain the
roof rights unless the roof had a מעקה. Ma'akeh. So אמר ליה
רבינא לרב אשי, Amar leh Ravina le-Rav Ashi, רבינא Ravina says to
רב אשי, Rav Ashi, תא שמע, Ta shema, another תא שמע, Ta
shema, דאמר ריש לקיש זאת אומרת המוכר בית לחבירו, De'amar Reish Lakish
zot omeret hamocher bayit lechavero, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said, this implies,
that is, from the previous ברייתא Braita that we had just quoted
earlier that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish referenced and said that implies when
you sell a house to your friend ואמר לו על מנת שדיוטא
העליונה שלי דיוטא העליונה שלו, Ve'amar lo al menat shediyuta ha'elyona sheli
diyuta ha'elyona shelo, that if the person mentions explicitly I want to
retain the construction rights on the roof top, then he does retain
the roof top building rights. Okay, ואמרינן למאי הלכתא, Ve'amrinan lemai hilchata,
and we said what does that come to teach us? רב זביד
אמר שאם רצה להוציא בה זיזין מוציא ורב פפא אמר משום שרצה
לבנות עלייה על גבה בונה, Rav Zvid amar she'im ratza lehotzi bah
zizin motzi ve-Rav Pappa amar mishum sheratza livnot aliya al gabah boneh,
that רב זביד Rav Zvid said it means you can add those
protrusions and רב פפא Rav Pappa meant you could even add a
second story. ואי סלקא דעתך בסתמא לא קני, Vei salka dach de'atach
bistama lo kani, and if you're going to tell me that when
you sell a house בסתמא Bistama without mentioning עומקא ורומא, Umka veruma
just to sell the house, לא קני, Lo kani, that you don't
sell the roof rights or the air rights or anything like that,
so למה לי על מנת? Lama li al menat? Why does ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish think you have to explicate that it should be
על מנת? Al menat? it has to be said on condition that
you are retaining the roof rights. If you think סתם stam selling
a house doesn't include the air rights, then why would he ever
have to make that explicit? אהני ליה על מנת דאי נפל הדר
בני ליה. ahani lei al menat de-ei nafal hadar banei lei. No,
because the clarification there is not that it's about the building rights
on the roof, but it's about that if it should collapse, then
who's responsible to rebuild it? That is, if the upper course, the
upper, like the little row of bricks along the top, that is
the upper story, so you may, you might have to clarify that
you want to build on the roof, but you would still retain
the liability normally, בסתמא, bi-stama, if we say, if we say because
we say, if סתם stam means we don't include עומקא ורומא, Umka
veruma, that is סתם stam just means the house itself, then the
upper course of bricks along the roof parapet would be retained by
the original owner not to allow him to build a second story
or to add זיזין, zizin, because if you didn't retain that right
explicitly, then you wouldn't be allowed to have any construction rights in
the air rights, but if some of that would collapse, you would
have to repair it. So it's for the סתם stam case. Right.
And then when he said על מנת... al menat... על מנת al
menat means he's even allowed construction rights. So what does, so what
do we get from that? It's a weird thing to say that
like when I sell something that like forevermore I'm like responsible. Right.
So presumably it's part of this question that we don't like סתם.
stam. We don't want our שטרות shtarot to be written סתם. stam.
So I think that's part of my gut feeling, especially from yesterday
and today, that part of the development of these legal legalese is
to say we want there to be a lot of precision and
clarification in the שטר. shtar. Because this last פשט pshat here is
that they're saying that the סתמא... stama... למה לי על מנת? lama
li al menat? So למה לי על מנת? lama li al menat?
למה לי על מנת דאי נפל הדר בני? lama li al menat
de-ei nafla hadar banei? Right. So meaning I the seller... if you
don't say על מנת, al menat, all you're agreeing to is if
it would collapse that you'll repair. And then why would you do
that anyway? If you don't say על מנת, al menat, that is
ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish על מנת al menat is על מנת al
menat I'm allowed to build a whole second story or I'm allowed
to build זיזין zizin or something. Wait a second. So whose על
מנת al menat is אהני ליה על מנת דאי נפל? ahani lei
al menat de-ei nafal? That's if you didn't say like ריש לקיש.
Reish Lakish. That is, what does סתם stam mean? So סתם stam
means אהני ליה על מנת דאי נפל הדר בני ליה ahani lei
al menat de-ei nafal hadar banei lei is how I'm understanding it
at least. I'm sorry. So what happens if you say... Look in
the רשב"ם, Rashbam, it's sort of... okay. Last line here, man. What
does על מנת al menat mean if he doesn't, if it doesn't
mean the seller is retaining rights to the use of the גג?
gag? It means he is, he is selling the house and telling
the buyer and you know what, if the top course falls, I'll
pay for the damage, I'll rebuild it, as an incentive to the
buyer to buy the house. That's what I thought it... Maybe that's
what it was. One second. הפירושא דמילתא דרב פפא כדפרישית. ha-perusha de-milta
de-Rav Pappa ke-difrishit. הכי גרסינן בפירוש רבינו חננאל דאי נפלה הדר בניה
לה. hachi garsinan be-ferush Rabbeinu Chananel de-ei nafla hadar banaya lah. לעולם
מסתמא לא קני לוקח רומא ודקאמר יתור תנא למה לי להכי אהני
דאי נפלה דיוטא הדר בני לה וכדפרישית לעיל דרב פפא לאו בבנין
על גבי דיוטא איירי אלא בבנין דיוטא עצמה אם תיפול כי נראה
שיטת שמואל זאת בעיני ויש שיטות אחרות ואין בהן ממש. le-olam mi-stama
lo kani lokeiach ruma ve-de-ka-amar yitur tena lama li le-hachi ahanei de-ei
nafla deyuta hadar banei lah u-ke-difrishit le-eil de-Rav Pappa lav be-binyan al
gabbei deyuta ayiri ela be-vinyan deyuta atzma im tipol ki nira shitat
Shmuel zot be-einai ve-yesh shitot acherot ve-ein ba-hen mamash. The רשב"ם Rashbam
isn't so happy either. The רשב"ם Rashbam thinks that based on רבינו
חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel and a few other things, so he thinks it
may be a limitation on רב זביד Rav Zvid and רב פפא
Rav Pappa to say you only means that when you're doing the
construction, if something will collapse, you have the liability to replace it
from the upper part, but not necessarily that you get to build
even to build a second story, things like that. It's backing off
the רב פפא Rav Pappa thing. But in the end, he says
there are lots of different interpretations of this and he's not happy
with any of them. He said that. So that's the way I...
that's the way it seemed to me, it's like the simple... I
hear what you're saying. It's a little bit tricky to understand. Right.
Why would you do that? Right. Like, nah, I'm not going to
buy your house, it's got all these problems. Listen, listen, buy the
house, here's the price, and you know what, if the thing on
the top, like, needs... I'll repair it. Not forever. Right. Like once
or whatever. Right. Buy my house. So, right. It seems very strange
to me either way. Both ways are strange. Listen to this issue
about rather than the responsibility, but the right to rebuild the roof.
Right. But the rebuilding, meaning the right to rebuild the roof also
means that... meaning what? Meaning he, in other words, he... if it's
the... then he gets the roof. Right, if he has the he
owns the roof and if the roof collapses, then he can rebuild
it and still have the roof. Right, well were they mutually owned
in other words? Well, meaning the, but the, the roof is the
ceiling. Right, we had all that stuff back in the second פרק,
perek, right? The roof is the ceiling. Right with the ovens and
how thick the plaster and everything like that. So I'm not sure
there's a... So I'm still not understanding what we say about עומקא
ורומא. umka ve-ruma, Sounds like in conclusion that עומקא ורומא, umka veruma.
if you sell a house סתם stam without mentioning עומקא ורומא, umka
veruma, it means you're selling just the house. Right, not the, the
upper terrace building is something that comes additionally, you have to clarify
with עומקא ורומא. umka veruma, And עומקא ורומא, umka veruma. it sounds
like means even תהום ארעא עד רום רקיעא. tehom ara ad ruma
lerakia. If you write עומקא ורומא, umka veruma, it's as if you
wrote how far it goes. Which is why did you not sell
the בור ודות bor vedus אף על פי שכתב לו, af al
pi shekasav lo, which is our next משנה? mishna? No, because they
changed the משנה mishna to say אף על פי שלא כתב לו
af al pi shelo kasav lo כמי שכתב דמי kemishekasav dami למקנה
le-mikneh, עומקא ורומא. umka veruma, That, so we'll have to deal with
a little bit more, maybe Rabbi Linzer, I'll tell Rabbi Linzer to
make sure to go over that from today's דף daf into the
משנה mishna tomorrow just because it'll make a little bit more sense
in context there. I hope everyone has a great day. I think
we'll stop there for now. Have a wonderful day. Bye-bye.